<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3779 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3779.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5652 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5652.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6480 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6480.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6485 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6485.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6481 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6481.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6488 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6488.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-sidrops-aspa-profile-08" ipr="trust200902">
    <front>

        <title abbrev="ASPA Profile"> A Profile for Autonomous System Provider Authorization </title>

        <author fullname="Alexander Azimov" initials="A"
            surname="Azimov">
            <organization>Yandex</organization>
            <address>
                <email>a.e.azimov@gmail.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Eugene Uskov" initials="E"
            surname="Uskov">
            <organization>JetLend</organization>
            <address>
                <email>eu@jetlend.ru</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Randy Bush" initials="R"
            surname="Bush">
            <organization>Internet Initiative Japan</organization>
            <address>
                <email>randy@psg.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Keyur Patel" initials="K"
            surname="Patel">
            <organization abbrev="Arrcus">Arrcus, Inc.</organization>
            <address>
                <email>keyur@arrcus.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Job Snijders" initials="J." surname="Snijders">
            <organization>Fastly</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street />
                    <code />
                    <city>Amsterdam</city>
                    <country>The Netherlands</country>
                </postal>
                <email>job@fastly.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Russ Housley" initials="R" surname="Housley">
            <organization abbrev="Vigil Security">Vigil Security, LLC</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>918 Spring Knoll Drive</street>
                    <city>Herndon</city>
                    <region>VA</region>
                    <code>20170</code>
                    <country>USA</country>
               </postal>
               <email>housley@vigilsec.com</email>
          </address>
        </author>
    
        <date />

        <keyword>BGP</keyword>
        <keyword>Route leak</keyword>
        <keyword>Hijacks</keyword>

        <abstract>
            <t>
                This document defines a standard profile for Autonomous System Provider Authorization in the Resource Public Key Infrastructure.
                An Autonomous System Provider Authorization is a digitally signed object that provides a means of validating that a Customer Autonomous System holder has authorized members of Provider set to be its upstream providers or provide route server service at internet exchange point.
                For the Providers it means that they are legal to send prefixes received from the Customer Autonomous System in all directions including providers and peers.
            </t>
        </abstract>

        <note title="Requirements Language">
            <t>
                The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
                "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
                "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
                BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and
                only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
            </t>
        </note>
    </front>

    <middle>
        <section title="Introduction" anchor="intro">
            <t>
                The primary purpose of the Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI) is to improve routing security.
                (See <xref target="RFC6480" /> for more information.)
                As part of this infrastructure, a mechanism is needed to validate that a AS has permission from a Customer AS (CAS) holder to send routes in all directions.
                The digitally signed Autonomous System Provider Authorization (ASPA) object provides this validation mechanism.
            </t>

            <t>
                The ASPA uses the template for RPKI digitally signed
                objects <xref target="RFC6488" />, which defines a
                Cryptographic Message Syntax (CMS) <xref
                target="RFC5652" /> wrapper for the ASPA content as well
                as a generic validation procedure for RPKI signed
                objects.  As ASPAs need to be validated with RPKI
                certificates issued by the current infrastructure, we
                assume the mandatory-to-implement algorithms in <xref
                target="RFC6485" />, or its successor.
            </t>

		<t>To complete the specification of the ASPA (see
		Section 4 of <xref target="RFC6488"/>), this document
		defines:
                <list style="numbers">
                    <t>
                        The object identifier (OID) that identifies the ASPA signed object.
                        This OID appears in the eContentType field of the encapContentInfo object as well as the content-type signed attribute within the signerInfo structure).
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The ASN.1 syntax for the ASPA content, which is the payload signed by the CAS.
                        The ASPA content is encoded using the ASN.1 <xref target="X680"/> Distinguished Encoding Rules (DER) <xref target="X690"/>.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The steps required to validate an ASPA beyond the validation steps specified in <xref target="RFC6488" />).
                    </t>
                </list>
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="The ASPA Content Type" anchor="content-type">
            <t>
                The content-type for an ASPA is defined as id-ct-ASPA, which has the numerical value of 1.2.840.113549.1.9.16.1.49.

                This OID MUST appear both within the eContentType in the encapContentInfo structure as well as the content-type signed attribute within the signerInfo structure (see <xref target="RFC6488" />).
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="The ASPA eContent" anchor="content">
            <t>
                The content of an ASPA identifies the Customer AS (CAS) as well as the Set of Provider ASes (SPAS) that are authorized to further propagate announcements received from the customer.
            </t>
            <t>
                Not all route servers at internet exchange points are transparent, e.g. in some cases they are present in the ASPATH.
                In this case route server AS is acting as provider AS, which propagates routes between its customers.
                Thus, a customer MUST add both upstream providers and route sever AS it is connected to its SPAS.
            </t>
            <t>
                If customer is connected to multiple transit providers/route servers they MUST be registered in a single ASPA object.
                This rule is important to avoid possible race conditions during updates.
            </t>
            <t>
                The eContent of an ASPA is an instance of ASProviderAttestation, formally defined by the following ASN.1 <xref target="X680"/> module:
            </t>

            <sourcecode type="asn.1" src="RPKI-ASPA-2022.asn"/>

            <t>
                Note that this content appears as the eContent within the encapContentInfo as specified in <xref target="RFC6488" />.
            </t>

            <section title="version">
                <t>
                    The version number of the ASProviderAttestation MUST be v0.
                </t>
            </section>

            <section title="customerASID">
                <t>
                    The customerASID field contains the AS number of the Autonomous System (AS) that authorizes a collection of provider ASes (as listed in the providerASSet) to propagate prefixes in the specified address family to other ASes.
                </t>
            </section>

            <section title="providers">
                <t>
                    The providers field contains the listing of ASes that are authorized to further propagate announcements in the specified address family received from the customer.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Each element contained in the providers field is an instance of ProviderAS.
                </t>
                <section title="ProviderAS">
                    <section title="providerASID">
                        <t>
                            The providerASID field contains the AS number of an AS that has been authorized by the customer AS to propagate prefixes in the specified address family to other ASes.
                        </t>
                    </section>
                    <section title="afiLimit">
                        <t>
                            The afiLimit field optionally constrains the authorization given to the provider AS to a single address family.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            If present, it contains the two-octet Address Family Identifier (AFI) for which the relation between the customer and provider is authorized.
                            AFI values are specified in <xref target="IANA-AF"/>.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            If omitted, the authorization is valid for both IPv4 and IPv6 announcements.
                        </t>
                    </section>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section title="ASPA Validation" anchor="validation">
            <t>
                Before a relying party can use an ASPA to validate a routing announcement, the relying party MUST first validate the ASPA object itself.
                To validate an ASPA, the relying party MUST perform all the validation checks specified in <xref target="RFC6488" /> as well as the following additional ASPA-specific validation step.
                <list style="symbols">
                    <t>
                        The autonomous system identifier delegation extension <xref target="RFC3779" /> is present in the
                        end-entity (EE) certificate (contained within the ASPA), and the customer AS number in the ASPA is
                        contained within the set of AS numbers specified by the EE certificate's autonomous system identifier
                        delegation extension.
                    </t>
                </list>
            </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
            <t>
                Please add the id-mod-rpki-aspa-2022 to the SMI Security for S/MIME Module Identifier (1.2.840.113549.1.9.16.0)
                registry (https://www.iana.org/assignments/smi-numbers/smi-numbers.xml#security-smime-0) as follows:
            </t>
            <figure>
                <artwork type="text">
    Decimal   | Description                   | Specification
    -----------------------------------------------------------
    TBD2      | id-mod-rpki-aspa-2022         | [ThisRFC]
                   </artwork>
            </figure>

            <t>
                Please add the ASPA to the SMI Security for S/MIME CMS Content Type (1.2.840.113549.1.9.16.1) registry
                (https://www.iana.org/assignments/smi-numbers/smi-numbers.xml#security-smime-1) as follows:
            </t>
            <figure>
                <artwork type="text">
    Decimal   | Description                   | Specification
    -----------------------------------------------------------
    49        | id-ct-ASPA                    | [ThisRFC]
                   </artwork>
            </figure>

            <t>
                Please add Autonomous System Provider Authorization to the RPKI Signed Object registry
                (https://www.iana.org/assignments/rpki/rpki.xhtml#signed-objects)
                as follows:
            </t>
            <figure>
                <artwork type="text">
    Name                                     | OID                         | Specification
    --------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
    Autonomous System Provider Authorization | 1.2.840.113549.1.9.16.1.49  | [ThisRFC]
                   </artwork>
            </figure>

            <t>
               Please add an item for the Autonomous System Provider Authorization
               file extension to the "RPKI Repository Name Scheme"
               registry created by <xref target="RFC6481"/> as follows:
            </t>
            <figure>
                <artwork>
<![CDATA[
   Filename
   Extension  RPKI Object                               Reference
   --------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
      .asa    Autonomous System Provider Authorization  [draft-ietf-sidrops-aspa-profile]
]]>
                </artwork>
            </figure>

        </section>

        <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
            <t>
                While it's not restricted, but it's highly recommended maintaining for selected Customer AS a single ASPA object that covers all connected providers/route servers.
                Such policy should prevent race conditions during ASPA updates that might affect prefix propagation.
                The software that provides hosting for ASPA records SHOULD support enforcement of this rule.
                In the case of the transition process between different CA registries, the ASPA records SHOULD be kept identical in all registries.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="Acknowledgments" title="Acknowledgments">
        </section>

    </middle>

    <back>
        <references title="Normative References">
            &RFC2119;
            &RFC3779;
            &RFC8174;
            &RFC5652;
            &RFC6485;
            &RFC6481;
            &RFC6488;

            <reference anchor="X680" >
                <front>
                    <title>Information technology -- Abstract Syntax Notation One (ASN.1): Specification of basic notation</title>
                    <author>
                        <organization>ITU-T</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date year="2015"/>
                </front>
                <seriesInfo name="ITU-T" value="Recommendation X.680"/>
            </reference>

            <reference anchor="X690" >
                <front>
                    <title>Information Technology -- ASN.1 encoding rules: Specification of Basic Encoding Rules (BER), Canonical Encoding Rules (CER) and Distinguished Encoding Rules (DER)</title>
                    <author>
                        <organization>ITU-T</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date year="2015"/>
               </front>
               <seriesInfo name="ITU-T" value="Recommendation X.690"/>
            </reference>

            <reference anchor="IANA-AF" target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/address-family-numbers/address-family-numbers.xhtml">
                <front>
                    <title>Address Family Numbers</title>
                    <author>
                        <organization>IANA</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date />
                </front>
               <!-- <seriesInfo name="Reachable from" value="http://www.iana.org/numbers.html"/> -->
            </reference>

        </references>

        <references title="Informative References">
            &RFC6480;
        </references>
    </back>
</rfc>
